This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SE-Radio.net.
SE Radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions of software
engineering topics at least once a
month.
SE Radio is brought to you by IEEE
Software Magazine, online at
computer.org/software.
This is Robert for Software Engineering
Radio.
I'm joined on the show today by Dr.
Michael Stonebraker.
Dr. Stonebraker is one of the leading
academic researchers in the field of
database technology. He earned his
doctoral degree from the University of
Michigan. He was a professor at the
University of California, Berkeley for
over 25 years and is now a professor at
the Massachusetts Institute of
Technology.
Dr. Stonebraker is the author of scores
of published research papers in academic
journals and is a recipient of numerous
awards, including the IEEE Von Neumann
Award.
Dr. Stonebraker is also one of the
leading entrepreneurs in the
commercialization of database
technology. He has founded six
venture-backed startups, is the
architect of the Postgres
and Ingres relational databases and is
the co-founder and CTO of VoltDB, the
industry sponsor of the open-source
VoltDB database.
Dr. Stonebraker, welcome to Software
Engineering Radio.
Thank you very much, Robert. Dr.
Stonebraker, please tell the listeners
more about your background. Well,
actually, I started nine venture
capital-backed companies, so your six
number is a little low.
Uh
as you said, I was on the faculty at the
University of California, Berkeley for
many years.
And uh in 1999,
uh we switched my wife and I switched
coasts.
And I've been at MIT since that time.
Uh
I am the main architect of the Ingres
database system, the Postgres database
system,
uh
a system called C-Store, which turned
into the Vertica
uh
database system now owned by
Hewlett-Packard, uh
H-Store, which turned into VoltDB, which
you mentioned earlier.
And uh I'm working on a variety of, you
know, new database projects and
other non-database stuff.
Uh so, I'm alive and well.
Your paper, One Size Fits All, an idea
whose time has come and gone,
you describe how the database market is
segmented.
Please summarize your views on how the
database market is segmented.
Okay, well, in that paper, which I
wrote, I believe in 2006,
7 years ago,
uh
you know, the basic point I was trying
to make was that
uh the hegemony of relational database
systems, which is, you know, during the
'90s,
uh one size fits all was was the answer.
Uh if you had a database problem, all
the major database vendors would say,
uh
you know, Oracle 9i or 11j, whatever the
current version was,
is the answer. Now, what was the
question? So, it was the whole uh
thinking was that the traditional
architecture,
uh you know, which is espoused by uh,
Oracle, SQL Server,
IBM's DB2.
That was the answer to all database
questions.
And in 2006,
I was trying to make the statement that
that wasn't true anymore.
Uh, in 2013, I'd like to make a much,
much, much stronger statement,
which is that the traditional
architecture is not good at anything.
And it's absolute totally obsolete
technology in the same way that IMS and
out of out of base and IDMS systems from
the '70s are obsolete technology.
And in every market segment I can think
of,
there is a much, much better solution,
uh,
either in terms of functionality or
performance.
And so, I view the
database market at a tipping point,
which is the major architecture being
sold by the vendors is just plain wrong.
And newer and better stuff is either
here or
just around the corner.
And that
uh, users, well, the database vendors
either are going to lose market share or
have to somehow
uh, pirouette from what they're
currently doing to completely different
software.
And users are going to face the same
kinds of transition pains.
Now, the reason I make this statement is
I would categorize the database market,
the entire database market, into three
pieces.
Uh, the first one uh, I would call the
data warehouse market. Uh, every major
company has a historical
uh
data store of customer-facing data that
they use business intelligence tools to
uh
to access. So, that's about round
numbers a third.
Uh
a third of the database market I would
characterize as, you know, OLTP, you
know, transaction processing.
Uh that is both
the traditional trans transaction
processing that we've known for years,
as well as all kinds of new TP issues.
Things like maintaining the state of
massively multiplayer in the internet
games is a big transaction processing
problem.
Uh you need to be able to move and shoot
at the same time, and you and 10,000
other people are inhabiting the same
uh the same geographical state.
Putting ads on in real time on internet
pages is another transaction processing
problem.
Uh
so, the the internet
uh and internet applications brings a
complete new realm
to TP applications.
In addition, the we are in the process
of sensor tagging everything of
significance. So, that includes marathon
runners,
uh
so, that we can make sure that nobody
cheats and and goes and hops on the
subway as Rosie Ruiz did in the Boston
Marathon quite a few years ago.
And, you know, MIT is thinking about
sensor tagging every library book.
Uh
they also are thinking of sensor tagging
every
uh physical uh repair that needs doing
on their physical plant. So, these
sensors generate, you know, mountainous
real-time feeds of data
and processing those feeds is another
OLTP problem.
Uh so, OLTP,
both new and old, is another sort of
third of the market.
Uh the remaining third
is a potpourri of other stuff. And that
includes
uh NoSQL systems, of which I guess
and
and Couch are probably the dominant
vendors at this point.
Uh
graph database systems such as Neo4j,
uh array database systems such as SciDB,
uh
Hadoop and its various instantiations.
And so, it's a third data warehouses, a
third OLTP, and a third everything else.
Now, the everything else piece is not
a traditional relational database market
at all, which is the you know, they
the relational vendors have no market
share in that 1/3.
Uh
in data warehouses,
it's crystal clear at this point
that the entire market is going to move
to column stores,
uh such as typified by Hana and Vertica
and ParAccel, systems like that.
Uh even Teradata is rumored to be
rewriting their DBMS to be a column
store.
So, row stores are are are not
competitive in that market and are going
to get replaced by column stores.
And that transition is
well along and happening.
And the reason is simple, column stores
are a factor of 50 or 100 faster than
row stores on the
traditional data warehouse problems.
So, the traditional architecture doesn't
work on data warehouses
and is going to get replaced by
something that's 50 or 100 times faster.
Uh that leaves the online transaction
processing market.
In the OLTP space,
uh that
what's what's occurring is that the size
of OLTP databases,
you know, is not that gigantic. It
basically goes up
at the rate that you sell more stuff.
On the other hand, main memory is
dropping in price like a rock.
And main memory is dropping faster than
OLTP database sizes are going up.
So, OLTP is in the process of becoming a
main memory database market and not a
traditional architecture market.
That's already being seen in products
such as HANA from SAP and Hekaton
uh from from Microsoft,
as well as systems like VoltDB, MemSQL,
SQLFire, uh things like that.
So,
so OLTP will be a main memory database
market.
Warehouses will be a column store market
and everything else is not a traditional
architecture market at all.
So, there's no place that I can see that
the traditional architecture is viable.
So, I see that it will
fade gradually fade into the sunset in
the same way that IMS and Adabas are
fading into the sunset.
You've told us that
the traditional database architecture is
on its way out.
Please summarize for us the main
characteristics of the traditional
row-based architecture.
Certainly, I should have done that at
the beginning.
Uh
So, the traditional architecture
is exemplified by
uh
DB2, SQL Server, Oracle, PostgreSQL,
Ingres.
Uh essentially, all the relational
database systems written more than a
decade ago.
Uh
Uh what all those systems have in common
is they store records on the disk,
meaning the next thing
in disk storage is the next attribute in
the same record.
So, they store data on the disk row by
row by row or record by record by
record.
Uh disk blocks are are substantially
encoded. Uh it's vendor specific exactly
how that's done,
but uh all systems heavily encode
uh disk blocks. For example,
uh records are stored with a record ID
at the front of the record.
There's usually a bitmap which indicates
the non-null fields.
Then the fixed-length fields are stored
followed by the variable-length fields.
So, so
the record structure is very disk-like.
Uh in main memory, there is a buffer
pool of disk blocks. So, where the disk
blocks sit in main memory
in
disk block format.
Uh the standard wisdom is to use
record-level locking
uh to deal with concurrency control.
And the traditional wisdom is to use a
write-ahead log uh to deal with crash
recovery. So, write ahead log dynamic
row level locking
is the way so-called acid is done.
Uh B-trees are omnipresent as the
indexing structure
and SQL is the language of choice.
There's a query optimizer
and a query executor, both of which are
row oriented.
And that architecture describes
perfectly all the traditional relational
database systems.
And at this level, they all look they
all look the same.
So, when I say the traditional
architecture, I mean that architecture.
Uh this was first promulgated by System
R, which is the which was the
predecessor of DB2
back in the '70s.
And has been used essentially intact
ever since.
Dr. Stonebraker, at a talk you gave here
in San Francisco,
you
demonstrated the results of some of your
research, which showed that databases
spend about 90% of their time
doing what could be described as
overhead and only 10%
on the actual value-producing activity
of reading and writing data. Please
describe the results of your research.
As I said,
uh if you have an OLTP
database,
chances are it fits in main memory.
And even if it doesn't, we can we can
turn to we can turn to dealing with that
in a minute.
If it fits in main memory and you're
using the traditional architecture,
then all of your data sits in the buffer
pool.
You know, in main memory.
So, And ran TPCC. This was I think in
2009,
which is the standard OLTP benchmark on
uh
the Shore uh DBMS, which is a an open
source traditional architecture
uh
system.
We use Shore only cuz we had the source
code and
Dave DeWitt, who was visiting MIT at the
time, wrote it, so he wanted to use it,
of course.
Uh
so we
but but it it has all of the elements of
the traditional architecture and
if we had profiled MySQL or Postgres,
they would have looked very similar.
So all the data's in the buffer pool. We
ran TPCC.
And we uh instrumented the code to say
where does all the time go?
And so in round numbers, uh what we
found out was that
less than 10% of the path length goes to
doing useful work, meaning actually
finding the record and updating it or
whatever else.
The remaining 90% is all overhead.
So
the overhead, roughly speaking, divided
into four equal-sized pieces of pie. Of
course, it
uh
they weren't all equal-sized, but they
were all all significant-sized.
Uh the first one was the overhead of
dealing with the buffer pool.
Uh as, you know, as you can imagine,
you have to pick a record out of the
buffer pool. You have to find a record
in the buffer pool, and then you have to
convert it from its encoded
disk-oriented format into main memory
format, so you can operate on it.
So you have to convert it uh into main
memory format and then if you update it,
convert it back out of main memory
format. In addition, you've got to
maintain a least recently used list of
buffer pool blocks so that you can evict
the right one at the right time.
You have to pin buffer pool blocks,
you know, when you have an active
pointer pointing into it. All of that
stuff in round numbers is one of the
four pieces of pie.
The second piece of pie is
every time you touch a record, you have
to set a read lock.
Every time you update that record, you
have to upgrade that lock to a write
lock.
Setting locks and maintaining the lock
table, looking for deadlocks in in the
lock table.
Locking is another of the four pieces of
pie.
The third piece of pie is every time you
write a record, you have to
write its before image and its after
image into a write-ahead lock.
So, the runtime cost of crash recovery
was another
of the pieces of pie.
The fourth piece of pie you have to
think about for a minute.
And so,
it it fourth piece of pie was
multi-threading overhead.
All of the major database systems are
multi-threaded.
Back in,
you know, the '80s,
when these decisions were made,
multi-threading was an awfully good idea
because if you
if you did a disk if you did a read and
the record you want wasn't in main
memory, you'd have to go fetch it off
the disk. You'd block, you'd want to
switch to doing something else.
And so, it's very useful to have other
threads around that could run.
And this was this was
completely to optimize the then
prevalent architecture.
Uh these days, we all of a sudden have a
lot more cores
uh sharing the same main main memory.
And database systems all have,
you know, shared data structures.
The most prevalent one is B-trees.
So, if we if we have 10 threads alive
doing useful work in a database system,
all sharing main memory, all sharing the
same database,
uh then you have 10 threads that may
well be traversing the same B-tree at
the same time.
If uh half of them are doing inserts,
you've got to make sure that you don't
corrupt that shared data structure.
So, to avoid corruption, uh there are a
variety of techniques, but most of them
involve latching
B-tree blocks that may well be updated
to keep other updaters from screwing
them up.
So, the latching and associated thread
weights
uh
that are associated with shared data
structures is another piece of the pie.
Uh B-trees are a shared data structure,
the lock table is a shared data
structure, resource management data
structures are also shared.
Uh temporary storage has to be malloc'd
and freed.
Uh
this So, there's just everywhere in
database systems, there are shared data
structures.
So, that's the other 90% of the path
length in
a traditional database system when
operating on data that is in the buffer
pool.
So, two things become completely
obvious.
The first one is that if you have some
fancy
replacement for B-trees that is faster
than B-trees,
and there are dozens of candidate data
structures that allow you to do searches
of the B-tree variety.
A better B-tree affects only 10% of the
path length.
Meaning, it's not worth doing. So, if
you're going to make a difference,
you've got to get You've got to worry
about overhead, and worrying about the
actual useful work
is just not worth it. So, worry about
where where the cycles go.
The second thing is
if you have a
database system,
and let's say it
it implements
data in main memory.
That gets rid of the buffer pool. That
slice of the pie is gone.
But, if you continue to be
multi-threaded,
do a write-ahead log,
and do dynamic record-level locking,
then those three slices of the pie are
still there.
So, if you take any one slice out of out
of this pie and say, "How much faster do
I go?"
The answer is, "Well, you go a little
bit faster, but it's a marginal win."
Clearly, all of those overhead factors
were introduced because they were
thought to be necessary.
How can you build a database with which
provides
acid without any of those
overhead sources?
Okay.
So, there's been
considerable research and a variety of
products
in the last
5 or 6 years
that are all attempting to do much
better, you know, in this regard.
So, I'll just go through
roughly what the ideas are.
Uh,
number one,
you cannot do record level locking. It
is just too expensive.
And all of the new main memory oriented
database systems,
none of them use record level locking.
So, the two other techniques that are
popular, some systems use what's called
multi-version concurrency control, which
is an optimistic concurrency control
system.
Some of them, including VoltDB, use
timestamp ordering.
So, you've got to use something else.
Don't even think about record level
locking.
Uh,
so that's that's that's the answer to
that piece of the pie.
The second piece of the pie
is, uh, has to do with crash recovery.
Uh,
a fair number of systems continue to use
continue to use traditional write-ahead
logging.
That's going to seriously impair their
ability to go fast.
Uh, that isn't what VoltDB does.
Uh,
and so,
uh,
VoltDB,
instead of doing data logging, which is,
uh,
if you update 10 records, then you write
the before image and after image of
those of those six records into a log,
and you have to push that log to disk.
Uh,
if instead you simply log
the command that was being run. So, if
you drive up to McDonald's and say,
"I'll have a number six with fries and a
diet coke."
If you're just logging the command, you
just log six fries, diet coke instead of
all the data effects of that
transaction.
So, Volt does what's called command
logging or transaction logging
which is wildly more efficient at run
time than data logging.
So, it shrinks that piece of the pie
down to a sliver
by simply doing logical logging at a
much, much higher level.
Now, of course, there's no free lunch
here.
Uh somehow there's got to be a cost to
command logging.
And there is, which is if you need to
roll forward from a crash
uh
then you can roll forward a data log way
faster than you can redo the commands
that
uh actually, you know, produce those
data effects.
So, recovery time is a lot slower.
On the other hand, essentially all
modern OLTP systems use replication to
produce high availability.
So, the only time you actually go down
is if you have a cluster-wide disaster
like a power failure.
So, command logging is is a very is an
is an efficient engineering trade-off
which shrinks that sliver down to a tiny
bit
uh and uses the fact that essentially
everybody wants HA
uh and therefore you almost never have
to recover from the command log.
So, that's sort of the second piece of
the pie and the way Volt gets rid of it.
Uh there may well be other ideas,
uh but but you've got to shrink shrink
the the size of the log way way down.
So, the third third piece of the pie is
of course the the buffer pool. All main
memory database systems get rid of that
completely. So, that that's just plain
gone.
And so, that that leaves you with the
fourth piece of the pie, which is, uh,
multi-threading.
And here there there are two main ideas.
Uh, the first idea, which is the one
Volt uses, is to say, "Don't
multi-thread. You know, it's too
expensive."
So, you're about to say, uh, "Haven't
you guys heard that, uh, multi-core
architectures are a big thing these
days?" And yeah, I've heard that.
So, what Volt does is if you have a
10-core system that shares
32 gigs of main memory,
uh, we divide up the 32 gigs into 10
pieces, assign each core
statically to one of those pieces, and
we treat a multi-core machine
as 10 single-core machines, and we run
those single-threaded.
So, there is no There are no latches.
There is no multi-threading in Volt.
So, that's one solution.
The other solution is to design what are
called latch-free data structures. In
other words, shared data structures that
don't require latches.
There's quite a bit of research in this
area, uh, and you know, if you're going
to move in either of these directions,
uh, you have to completely start from
scratch and write a new database system.
Uh, the traditional vendors will not be,
you know, will not be able to use either
of these without uh, gigantic, uh,
rewrites.
So, those are kind of the ideas that
seem plausible. And
I've mentioned the ones that uh Volt is
actually using.
You mentioned two
protocols to avoid um
locking, the timestamp ordering and
multiversion concurrency control.
Sure.
tell us a little bit about how those
work?
Sure.
Uh
So, let's start with multiversion
concurrency control.
Uh so, the idea is that I have a
transaction
and I'm going to assume that
my transaction is going to succeed.
So, I'm just going to go through
running exit I'm going to execute this
whole transaction from beginning to end.
And I'm going to make a note of
everything my transaction reads. And I'm
going to make a note and I'm of course
going to write uh
whenever I do a write I'm going to write
the new values. Uh the key thing here is
I'm not going to write them over
uh what used to be there. I'm going to
write them, you know,
in in a new place.
So, basically
So, basically I go to the end of the
transaction
and at the end I note everything I've
read and I've and everything I've
written goes to think of it as a side
file.
Uh at the end I then check to see
whether
I had any problem with this transaction.
In other words,
did anybody
did anybody write anything
that I read
uh
that committed before me. So, I
basically check at the very end to see
whether everything went okay.
And the idea is that in a well-designed
database system, 99% of the time
transactions succeed.
Cuz otherwise, you don't get anything
done.
So, that's the general idea is that
commit time, you go and look and see if
there's any problem.
This is what's called optimistic, which
is the complete converse
of dynamic locking, which is
pessimistic, which is
in in dynamic locking, you wait if there
might be any problem.
Uh and so, you come up against something
that might be a problem, and you just
stop and wait to see whether it was
okay.
In in
optimistic concurrency control or
multi-version concurrency control, you
just continue to the end on the
assumption that it you know, it isn't
going to be a problem.
And I think if your data is on disk,
the
simulation studies from many, many years
ago showed that dynamic locking worked
better.
Uh but I think all the conditions have
changed and in main memory, that isn't
true. So, that's one possible approach.
The second approach is to order the
transactions
1 2 3 4 5,
and make sure that they're done in
perfect order. And usually, that
ordering is done using a clock. And so,
a transaction just reads the clock, and
transactions are then executed serially
in clock order, and therefore, there are
no uh contention problems.
Uh that was the scheme Volt used to use.
Uh they found out that
they have a much more sophisticated
scheme now
that doesn't require you to you to
synchronize clocks across multiple
systems.
And so that requires a blackboard for me
to tell you exactly how it works.
But anyway,
you either order the transactions
uh
1 2 3 4 5 either based on a clock or
based on some other mechanism.
Or you use optimistic concurrency
control and check at the end if anything
bad happened.
You discussed partitioning the data
by core.
How does a system like this handle
transactions
including data that is pinned to
different cores?
Right. So here again, this this is this
is a piece of Pragma.
Which is
if you have if you're trying to do a
million transactions a second
to a one record database
there is simply no way to do it because
everybody needs to update the same
thing.
The extension of this is if you have 10
records in a 10 record database
and you put one record on each of 10
nodes
and then you try and
run a million transactions a second,
each of which updates all 10 records,
all hell will break loose
because every transaction crosses
node boundaries
and concurrency control becomes
extremely difficult.
And requires things called two-phase
commits
and
basically just think expensive.
So, anyone who does who has an
application that does a lot of
distributed transactions, meaning
transactions that cross
chunk boundaries or cross node
boundaries,
uh that's fundamentally expensive.
And so, what most everybody figures out
one way or another
is how to design applications
that where most of the transactions go
to a single chunk.
Cuz otherwise, you pay a a big
performance penalty.
So, the answer is Volt Volt is optimized
for the case that most transactions
uh go to a single chunk.
And Volt is blindingly fast in that
case.
We, of course, continue to do any
transactions,
but the synchronization
for multi-
multi-chunk transactions, you know, has
to be paid.
Would please drill down into how VoltDB
uses multiple nodes to ensure high
availability?
Sure.
So, so,
20 years ago,
i- if you
if you went to an OLTP system,
uh
and executed a transaction,
chances are it was running on a sing- on
a single-node machine.
And if that node crashed,
well, the whole idea was you get back up
as quickly as you can,
and you're just down for however long
you're down.
And so, that was the routine
solution, which is get back up as
quickly as you can,
and, you know, and in the meantime, you
know, you're just losing revenue.
Uh
these days
no one I know of is willing to pay down
time.
Uh
and and if Amazon or eBay goes down,
they're on the front page of the New
York Times.
So, anybody who cares is now willing to
buy
backup hardware
and fail over
to a backup copy of the data.
So, Tandem Computers, you know, sort of
worked all of this out, you know, 15 or
20 years ago.
And so, basically, you you run multiple
replicas.
You have
uh
you have two copies of everything or
three copies of everything.
However many copies you want.
Do you want to run with a belt or a belt
and suspenders or belt, suspenders, and
a rope?
You know, it's your choice how many
replicas to run.
And then the idea is the database system
makes sure that it implements all the
replicas. It that you know, it basically
does all updates on all replicas.
And if a node goes down, you simply fail
over and continue processing
uh using a different replica. And VoltDB
does this.
If there's a failure, you never see it.
It's completely masked.
And this seems to be table stakes these
days and anybody who's serious about
OLTP, just no one is willing to take
down time.
Do the nodes use a distributed consensus
protocol to ensure consistency of data?
A great topic. Great topic, Robert.
So,
the
NoSQL guys,
basically said
uh
well, let's just use eventual
consistency.
Which is to say
uh I'll I'll if let's say there's two
copies of Robert's salary
uh one in San Francisco and one in
Boston
we'll update the one in San Francisco.
We'll give Robert you know, the a I did
it.
And then we'll propagate uh that update
to uh the East Coast at our leisure.
And so
the idea was that well, if you just
stopped accepting new updates eventually
the two copies of the database would be
the same.
Uh
so the
NoSQL vendors basically promulgated the
idea that we'll make the database
eventually consistent
but it isn't consistent in real time.
What this actually means
is that
the database
uh
can be completely trashed.
Uh and so let me give you a quick
example.
Let's say that there is exactly one
widget remaining in your warehouse.
And so you have two two copies of that
of the state of the warehouse.
You know, one in San Fran- cisco, one in
Boston.
So let's say that uh Robert, you log in
to San Francisco and you say, "Oh,
there's one widget." And you buy it.
So uh you now
get a commit that you bought the widget.
And so uh
and at its leisure the database system
sends the
the the you bought the widget to Boston.
Uh let's say before it arrives, or let's
say there's a network partition, or some
other bad thing happens.
And or even that San Francisco fails.
You now have the Boston database which
thinks there's one widget.
And so I log into the Boston database,
see that there's one widget, and I buy
it.
And I get a commit saying, "Yep, you
bought the widget."
So you now have Robert and Michael both
thinking they bought the last widget.
Eventual consistency will say the the
ultimate state of the database
is there's minus one widget in
inventory.
Which is clearly an unacceptable state.
So eventual consistency
doesn't work.
It doesn't work in technical terms.
It doesn't work for any transactions
that are not commutative. It only works
if things can be executed in any order
and always give the same answer.
And that's rarely true as the widget
example shows.
So if you run replicas with eventual
consistency, meaning you don't guarantee
acid for your replicas,
then
you risk garbaging the database.
So Volt doesn't do that.
Uh, you've got to make sure in my
opinion, the right way to deal with
replicas is to say acid is the answer,
replicas are in fact consistent.
So
there are two ways to do that. Uh, the
first way
is is
and this this gets this gets into some
gory details. So I'll I'll try and stay
out of the gore.
Uh
there's kind of two ways to to update
replicas.
The first way is you run the command
at San Francisco and you run the command
at Boston. So, you run the transaction
twice,
once at each replica.
And this is what's called active-active
replication.
So, that's solution one.
Solution two is you select one site as
the primary, say San Francisco.
You run the transaction in San
Francisco, and then you reliably
send the log over the network to Boston,
and you roll the log forward.
So, that's what's called active-passive.
The primary site is doing all the work,
and uh
the secondary site is just rolling
forward.
So, you can do both of these
transactionally.
Uh the details get a little bit messy,
but uh
this requires things called two-phase
commits.
My strong suspicion is that
active-active is way faster than
active-passive.
The reason for that is way back to the
slices of pie,
you don't want to write a log. You just
don't want to write a log.
And so And so, I'm a big fan of
active-active, which is what VoltDB
does.
And we make sure that the command
uh
is performed at both sites or at neither
site.
So, I'm a I'm a I'm a huge fan of
consistency.
You've been discussing the way that
multiple nodes provide
uh high availability.
Is the system also using multiple nodes
to increase throughput.
Of course. I mean, I think I think the
Again, this I think is table stakes.
Uh if you don't scale,
you're you're nowhere.
Because,
you know, the the standard example is
you're an internet startup,
and
you hit the hockey stick of growth,
and you want the database system to be
able to expand as your needs expand.
The only way to do that is what's called
scale out, which is just add more and
more and more nodes
uh as you need more horsepower.
So, I think scale out is the answer,
and high availability just essentially
comes for free with scale out.
So, any data any database system that's
a single node database system, I think
will not find success uh in the OLTP
market.
You've been a critic of some respects of
the NoSQL movement. Could you elaborate
on your criticisms?
What's going on in the NoSQL world?
Well, if you look at the primary NoSQL
advocate, it's a guy named Jeff Dean at
Google.
Uh
and Jeff Dean was
has written many papers. He's with main
architect of Bigtable, and was one of
the principal architects of MapReduce.
So, he recently wrote a system called
Spanner.
And Spanner, he makes a big point of
saying, is a complete asset replica
system.
He He has gotten the religion.
Uh so, Google users have just said, "I
want consistency, make it happen.
So, I think the
replica consistency,
you know,
gives users a guarantee about what their
data looks like.
Anything else does not.
And I think the NoSQL guys are going to
move fairly quickly to joining the ACID
bandwagon.
The second thing that is happening
fairly quickly is that
the NoSQL guys all said NoSQL
meant, you know, they wanted to have a
low-level low-level record at a time
language.
And that was what and Couch and
all the other guys started out with.
Uh very quickly, they realized that
their users wanted high-level
utterances.
And both Cassandra and
have
specified high-level languages
uh
to which, you know, you can uh access uh
their respective databases.
And these two languages, unless you
squint,
look exactly like SQL.
So, I think the NoSQL guys are moving
way closer to the SQL camp.
And uh my my sense is the NoSQL guys
started out being NoSQL.
Then they turned into not only SQL.
And I think now I would specify them as
not yet SQL.
But I think the differences between the
NoSQL guys and the SQL guys will be will
diminish dramatically over time.
Dr. Stonebraker, you've presented a lot
of really interesting ideas about where
the database market has been and where
it's going.
If you were to teach undergraduates a
database course today, what would you
cover?
Yeah, I think this is this is a really
interesting topic because I think
all database textbooks
have the traditional wisdom.
And in fact, the MIT database course
spends 2/3 of the course on the
traditional wisdom.
And that's true of essentially all the
other
uh universities I know of.
So, we are all teaching the wrong stuff.
And so, what I would do is I would teach
column stores, I would teach main memory
databases.
I would explain
what the advantages of graph databases,
array database systems
uh are. I would talk about the NoSQL
movement. You've also been critical of
Hadoop, but is there a place for it for
the right set of problems?
Okay. So, Hadoop.
Well, let me just be crystal clear what
Hadoop means.
Uh Hadoop is really a three-level stack.
At the bottom level is HDFS,
which is a file system.
Uh on top of that is an open-source
implementation of MapReduce,
which is what Hadoop has historically
called.
So, that implements a map and a reduce
and a protocol for processing
uh
MR-style queries.
So, this is uh this has been well
described in the literature and by the
Google guys, and Hadoop is basically the
open-source copy of that.
On top of that, there are a variety of
tools,
of which the most popular are probably
Hive and Pig.
Uh
and Hive and Pig basically think think
of them as SQL.
So, it's a three-level stack, sort of
SQL
implemented on top of MapReduce on top
of a file system.
So, that that's the stack.
Now,
90 more than 95%
of the Facebook workload, and Facebook
is a huge user of Hadoop,
comes in through Hive.
So, 95% of the traffic is SQL.
Uh
5% or less is
uh
commands that go directly to the
MapReduce layer.
So, here's what's happening as I see it.
If you run Hive on top of the MapReduce
layer on top of HDFS,
and you're specifying queries in Hive or
let's just let's just call it SQL.
Uh
then
then that stack runs wildly slower
than any parallel database system.
So, you will get horrible performance
relative to any of the data warehouse
products.
So, that's the go slow command
by a factor of 50 or 100.
And there's some very
very good technical reasons why that's
happening.
And if you open up any of the parallel
database systems, and you know, I've
opened up a bunch of them, and in fact,
I wrote one, Vertica,
they have nothing that looks like a
MapReduce layer in their innards. That
just isn't an interesting interface in a
parallel database system.
So, 95% of the time you are way better
off using something other than
the traditional Hadoop stack.
Uh and in fact,
the main proponents of Hadoop, which I
call Cloudera, Hortonworks, and
Facebook,
all figured this out.
And they are all writing or have written
Hive implementations
that get rid of the Hadoop layer
completely.
So, for instance, Cloudera has a system
called Impala that's out in the market
now.
Impala is an implementation of Hive
that does not use the the
the middle piece, the MapReduce piece at
all, cuz it's
it's it's a problem. It's a huge
problem.
So, the Hadoop proponents are in the
process of throwing Hadoop overboard.
So, so I think what will happen is that
the 95% of the traffic
that comes in through Hive
is going to go through a traditional
database like parallel database like
stack,
which will have nothing to do with this
MapReduce Hadoop layer.
So, it will, to a first approximation,
vanish.
Uh
and that will leave you with a
you know, that will leave you with two
choices.
Choice number one is run
run one of the data warehouse products,
you know, Teradata, Vertica,
Netezza, dot dot dot,
or run
uh one of the
SQL implementations from the Hadoop
players like Cloudera, Hortonworks, or
Facebook.
Uh
the Hadoop players will be implementing
on top of HDFS,
which has some horrible performance
problems of its own.
So, uh I expect the traditional data
warehouse vendors will still cream these
guys
uh in terms of implement in terms of
performance.
But, what will happen is that the
Hadoop vendors will start to look like
very traditional data warehouse vendors.
So, they will move way closer
to what looks like a parallel SQL
database system.
So, that's 95% of the load.
Uh 5% of the load
uh is what I would call embarrassingly
parallel map reduce style jobs.
And my best example is if you have a
million documents,
and you want to find all the documents
that have strawberry followed within
five words by vanilla,
well, divide up the million documents
over however many nodes you want to
process on,
write a Python script
uh that paws over
uh the documents on each node, do that
all in parallel,
uh and then you have a roll up at the
end.
So, this is an example of an
embarrassingly parallel job.
Those run beautifully in in map reduce,
and will run beautifully in in the
traditional Hadoop stack.
Uh
but, that's 5% or less of your workload.
So, if you are a Hadoop enthusiast,
make sure that uh
you're the workload you're trying to run
on the traditional Hadoop stack
is in this embarrassingly parallel
category.
If it's not, you're in for a world of
hurt
cuz you're going to have horrible
performance problems
uh
when you go up to
well
if you don't have one a problem that
looks like this, chances are you'll be
uh writing stuff in Hive
and you're going to have horrible
performance problems when you try and
scale.
And so, what will happen is
all the vendors will be there to pick up
the pieces.
Uh
all of the data warehouse vendors have
have or will soon have Hive interfaces,
so they can say just
just shove our our parallel database
system underneath this this lousy stack
that you started out with.
Uh
the
uh cloud the
Hadoop vendors will be selling you
things like Impala, which are, you know,
completely different implementations.
So,
you will switch out the innards of of
the traditional open-source Hadoop stack
in favor of something else.
My advice to you is if you were in
the 5% category, you're fine. Continue
to use
uh the traditional open-source stack. If
you're in the 95%
uh you don't want to go down the Hadoop
road at all. You want to figure out how
you're going to scale and where you're
going to end up and go directly there.
Dr. Stromberg, I'd like to spend the
last part of the interview talking about
Volt DB. Would you tell us a little bit
about the company?
Uh
so, Volt Volt is Volt is a startup that
that I founded
uh
5 years ago, 4 years ago.
Uh
it it's intention was to
uh take the
H-Store prototype that we wrote at MIT
and commercialize it in the in the
process
robustizing and
you know
and solidifying the code, adding command
logging
uh
adding much more SQL than was there
before adding uh dynamic elasticity so
you can add add resources, i.e. nodes,
on the fly without going down.
Uh
and so there's a long laundry list of of
things that they have done and others
that they are continuing to do.
The company's about 25 people.
Uh
we are
we are very busy. Uh sales are great. Uh
there's
there's a huge huge market for what we
do and
the places that we found early
acceptance uh
number one is maintaining the state uh
of internet games.
So things like leaderboards
things like uh the state of multiplayer
games
are very high performance OLTP problems
and so we're finding great success
there.
Uh we're finding success on Wall Street
where people want to
uh in in the midst of electronic trading
platforms uh people want high speed
OLTP.
Another example where we found
acceptance
is if you're in financial services and
you're maintaining
uh electronic trading desks all over the
world
uh the CEO of your company wants to
maintain your real-time exposure
to any given security,
uh, so that he can he can limit risk to
an acceptable amount. So, you want to
maintain the real-time position
worldwide
for every security on the planet, what
your your company's position is, uh,
short or long of that given security.
That's a high-performance OLTP problem.
Those are the places we found early
acceptance.
I think we're, you know, so-called new
SQL systems, of which Volt is an
example,
are crossing the chasm and finding
finding acceptance in,
you know, we in general OLTP problems,
and say the market I think is time
ginormous.
Who are some of the other players in the
new SQL space?
Uh, sure. So, I think, uh, number one,
both Hana and Hana from SAP,
uh, is not quite there yet, but it will
be a main memory OLTP system,
uh,
in a year or two.
Hekaton is coming out in at the end of
this year in SQL Server 14, I think is
the next release.
It's a main memory database system.
I think both of these systems are going
to have
performance issues that, uh,
that will mean Volt will run way faster
than they do.
Uh, other players are SQL Fire, uh,
which is,
uh,
which is now owned by Pivotal, used to
be spun out of EMC,
written by VMware.
Uh, so SQL Fire is another contender.
Uh, NuoDB is a startup, uh here in the
Boston area.
Uh, MemSQL is a startup on the West
Coast.
Uh,
so those those are some of the players.
If I'm not mistaken, VoltDB is open
source. Is that right?
Correct.
So, I think here I'd like to make a
general comment,
which is I think
until maybe 2007
or 2008,
it was essentially impossible to get a
venture capitalist to back
a system software company that was doing
open source software.
Uh,
that all changed with Red Hat. You know,
they paved the way for
showing that you could you could make a
financially viable proposition with open
source software.
So, I think most of the database systems
written in the last five or six years
are open source.
And I'm a huge fan of this business
model.
And it has nothing to do with
being altruistic. Uh,
my
you know, this is all about the sales
channel.
So, if you have a traditional closed
source
uh,
piece of system software,
well, you hire
a bag carrying, meat eating uh,
you know,
beer swigging salesman
who makes about $250,000
a year at quota.
However, he he is an expert at taking
the customer to lunch, not in explaining
technical nuances of his product.
So, you pair him with what's called a
sales engineer
who makes 150k at quota.
And so, you have what's called a
four-legged sales team
who with their management and overhead
is making around half a million dollars
a year
uh
as their cost.
Uh
customers have figured out that once
they buy an expensive piece of
proprietary software, they're really
hooked.
So, their whole idea is to get as much
freebies out of out of the sales team up
front as possible.
So, they will try and make you write
their application if they if they can.
And just generally squeeze you uh as
much as they can before they sign on the
dotted line.
They've also figured out that the
software goes on sale the last day of
the quarter.
So, they wait to negotiate until the
last day of the quarter of whatever your
quarter is
uh and so
every proprietary
system software company brings in the
majority of its quarterly revenue in the
last week of the quarter.
Uh
and has this very, very expensive sales
process that
that consumes
you know, 40, 50% of revenue just making
the sale. So, it's just a very expensive
sales channel
that's very unpredictable.
Uh it tends to result in customers
getting bad customer support
cuz the meeting-eating salesman is on to
the next deal the minute he signs you
and has no incentive to keep you happy.
So, I've been associated with company
after company that have had the sales
channel and I really hate it
cuz it's just a very, very expensive way
to make a sale.
Uh open source works completely
differently.
You drive customers to your website, you
say download the code see if you like
it.
Uh
and you get the customer doing his own
sales evaluation rather than you sending
out this four-legged sales team.
So,
uh and you don't do free be free pilots.
This allows you to have way way lower
sales costs and therefore way way lower
prices.
So, I think it's it's a it's a way that
everybody wins.
It's just a much more efficient sales
channel that results in much much lower
prices.
If listeners are interested in reading
some of your research or learning more
about you,
where's the best place for them to go?
The simple answer is if you Google my
name, you'll get to a site called
CiteSeer
that has my complete uh complete resume
with pointers to essentially everything
I've ever written. In in in addition, I
do actually blog for for ACM on an
irregular basis.
So, if you go to the ACM uh website,
there is
there is some
some blogging information there. If
listeners would like to learn more about
VoltDB,
how can they do that?
There's all kinds of information on the
website including how to get more
information.
Dr. Michael Stonebraker, thank you very
much for speaking to Software
Engineering Radio.
This is a lot of fun, Robert. Thank
thanks and I want to compliment you on
on the sophistication of your questions.
Thank you so much. Okay.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more
information about the podcast including
other episodes, visit our website at
se-radio.net.
To support us, you can advertise SE
Radio by clicking the Digg, Reddit,
Delicious, or Slashdot buttons on the
site, or by talking about us on
Facebook, Twitter, or your own blog.
If you have feedback specific to an
episode, please use the commenting
feature on the site so that other
listeners can respond to your comments
as well.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under the Creative Commons
2.5 license. Please see the website for
details. Thanks again for your support.